Guide to the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts
1802-1960
1831-1840
GEN MSS 982
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
28.95
(86 boxes) + 1 roll.
The Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts collection contains papers of both Alexis de Tocqueville and Gustave de Beaumont, intermixed. The papers include correspondence, personal papers, and autograph manuscripts by Tocqueville (including the autograph manuscript of De La Democratie en Amerique), Beaumont, and their families and associates, as well as autograph copies of Tocqueville and Beaumont documents by contemporary and later copyists, and photoduplicated copies of originals held elsewhere in other public and private collections.
Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1805-1859
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For information about Yale's acquisition of the materials which make up the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts, consult the curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 3: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Alexis de Tocqueville (1805-1859), French politician and author, best known for his Democracy in America (1835, 1840).
Scope and Contents
The Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts contains papers of both Alexis de Tocqueville and Gustave de Beaumont, intermixed. The papers include holograph manuscripts by Tocqueville (including the manuscript of De La Démocratie en Amérique), Beaumont, their families and associates, as well as holograph copies by contemporary and later copyists, and photo-duplicated copies of originals held elsewhere.
The collection includes correspondence and documents relating to Tocqueville's and Beaumont's visit to the United States, 1831-32, and investigations of the American penitentiary system.
Locations of some originals from which the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts copies were made are unknown. Some are known or believed to have been destroyed. For further information, contact the curator.
Table of Abbreviations Used in this Catalogue
Bonnel - "Instituteur" at the Elementary School, Tocqueville, Manche. The copies of the Tocqueville Tocqueville Mss. (i.e., Tocqueville manuscripts at the Tocqueville chateau, see below) were made almost entirely by him: first, for Neal Lambert White (below), then for Prof. John M. S. Allison and the White Collection on deposit in the library, then for GWP and the Yale Library. Until 1930 virtually all his copying was done into bound cahiers or copybooks. Then he used some long, lined legal- size sheets for additional items required by GWP. His hand is very clear and unmistakable. He was a faithful but not very imaginative copyist. He attempted to indicate when the original was not in Alexis de Tocqueville's hand.
Bt. - Gustave de Beaumont (1802-1866).
Bt. la Ch. - The chateau de la Borde, Beaumont la Chartre, Sarthe. The family Gentilhommiere of Beaumont's parents and his own home in later life. (now sold)
Doysie - Abel Doysie, in charge of having copies of French Diplomatic Archives made for the Library of Congress. His secretaries made the copies for White (below) of the Tocqueville American Manuscripts which White found at Redier's office in Paris and set aside temporarily to be copied. These copies were well done by two women: Mme. Desorments and Mademoiselle Anacreon (Mme. Jouhet) on long, lined, legal-size sheets, using the key numbers of White's inventory 3W (1920-1921) (see E.IV.e.).
Fabius - Emmanuel Fabius of Paris, joint owner of many Lafayette manuscripts, and donor of some Tocqueville items to GWP in 1956.
GWP - George Wilson Pierson, who began working on the Yale Tocqueville Archive in 1928 or 1929.
H. - Harvard (Widener) Library.
HJC - Harold Jefferson Coolidge.
HSP - Historical Society of Pennsylvania
Hunt. - Huntington Library, California.
Jardin - Andre Jardin: See E IV.e for information re A.J.; also see E.VI.e.8.
Langavant - Mme. de Langavant of St. Malo, a descendant of Beaumont's brother, Achille.
Larminat - Madeleine (Mme. Michel) de Larminat, daughter of Mme. de Beaumont-Hennocque and great grand-daughter of Gustave de Beaumont. Donor or vendor of most of the Beaumont manuscripts in the Yale Tocqueville Mss., 1953, 1955, 1956, 1964, 1969, 1973.
LC - Library of Congress: Ms. Division.
MHS - Massachusetts Historical Society.
NYHS - New York Historical Society.
Photo - Photograph or photostat.
Pub. Arch. C. - Public Archives of Canada.
Redier - Antoine Redier, author of Comme disait M. de Tocqueville ... (1926), in whose Paris office White found many Tocqueville manuscripts.
Redier Mss. - Tocqueville manuscripts in Redier's Paris office in the years 1920-21.
Robson - Prof. Robson, formerly working on Francis Lieber at the Huntington library (Hunt).
Romanet - Romanet family, branch of Bt. family.
Stoffels - Stoffels family - especially Mlle. Stoffels d'Hautefort.
T. & B. in Am. - Tocqueville and Beaumont in America (1938) by GWP.
Tocqueville - Alexis de Tocqueville (1805-1859).
Tocqueville Tocqueville Mss. - His Mss. at Tocqueville chateau in the years 1929-31.
White - Paul Lambert White (1890-1922). It was White who, as a beginning instructor at Yale, first looked up the Tocqueville and Beaumont families, saw Tocqueville and Beaumont Mss. at Tocqueville, at Redier's Paris office and perhaps also in the hands of the Beaumont family, and made three catalogues (plus some extracts and translations) and started having copies made for Yale by Bonnel and by Doysie's copyists.
Democracy -- United States; Prisons -- United States; Representative government and representation -- United States; Republicanism -- United States; Slavery -- United States; Travelers' writings, French; United States -- Description and travel; United States -- Economic conditions -- To 1865; United States -- Foreign public opinion, French; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1865; United States -- Social conditions -- To 1865; United States -- Social life and customs -- 1783-1865; Women -- United States -- Social conditions -- 19th century; Beaumont, Gustave de, 1802-1866; Beaumont, Gustave de, 1802-1866 ( Du système pénitentiaire aux Etats-Unis et de son application en France); Pierson, George Wilson, 1904-1993; Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1805-1859; Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1805-1859 ( De la démocratie en Amérique)
- TOCQUEVILLE & BEAUMONT, 1802-1831; A.
  - Tocqueville family background, education, character, 1
    - a. pamphlet, Episodes de la Terreur, posthumous publication (1867, 1901) by Tocqueville's father, Herve de Tocqueville (Box 1)
    - b. copy of acte de naissance of Alexis de Tocqueville extracted from Register of first arrondissement, Paris l an XIII de la Republique. (1 p., given GWP by Fabius.) (Box 1)
    - c. ALS Paris le 24 fevrier 1830 from Comte Herve de Tocqueville, pair de France (father of Alexis de Tocqueville). Asks King for additional pension for a man... a charge that would not long endure "car a 78 ans on a peu d'avenir." Apparently granted. (Given GWP by Fabius) Jardin comments: "L'intervention du Comte Herve pour la mise a la retraite du vieux Juge Lafontaine est interessante, parce qu'a ce moment l'ancien prefet s'efforce de faire avancer dans le tribunal son fils Alexis." (Box 1)
    - d. see also below: -A.IV. Tocqueville and Beaumont Correspondence, 1803-1829. -E.IV.a. G. W. Pierson notes on Tocqueville and Beaumont youth. -E.IV.e. White Catalogue 2W. (Box 1)
    - e. Catalogue des livres de la bibliotheque du chateau de Tocqueville, avril 1818. (Xerox copy: original sent to Andre Jardin for the Tocqueville archives) (Box 1)
  - Beaumont family background, education, character, 2
    Related Archival Materials note
    -see E.IV.a. GWP notes on Tocqueville and Beaumont youth.
    -Consult also Mme de Larminat, Alvis Tinnin, Seymour Drescher
    -see D.V. and E.VI.
    - a. Documents on the Beaumont family (Larminat to GWP) (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      - ownership of the Chateau de la Borde, from the 17th century to 1958 (as typed by Madeleine de Larminat) (Larminat to GWP)
      - lettres patentes of 9bre and Xbre 1813, naming one duchess, four counts and a number of barons, among the counts being De la Bonniniere de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
    - b. Correspondence of Beaumont's father, Comte Jules de Beaumont, and of Beaumont's mother, Rose Preau de La Baraudiere (Box 1)
      -undated letter, dimanche matin, identified by Mme de Larminat as from the Marquise de Beaumont, his mother, to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -Londres, ce 11 fevrier "1803," Charles to Jules de Beaumont, with postscript by Oct. [?] de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -Wessenkirke, ce 4 fevrier "1806," O. [?] de Beaumont to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce mercredi, 20 aout 1806, Preau de La Baraudiere to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -Arras, le 28 juin, Achille [?] to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -St. Cloud, ce 21 juillet 1809 9 Leopold de Beaumont to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce mercredi, Gustave's mother to his father [1821?] (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce lundi, 16 avril, Gustave's mother to his father (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce dimanche soir, 22 (postmarked 26 avril 1821), Gustave's mother to his father (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce mercredi soir, Gustave's mother to his father (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce lundi matin, 30 (3 mai 1821 postmark), Rose Preau de La Baraudiere to her husband, Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce lundi, 7 mai (1821 postmark), Gustave's mother to his father (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce samedi matin, 19 mai (1821 postmark), letter probably from Rose Preau de La Baraudiere to Gustave's father, Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -Carcassonne, le 13 9bre 1822, Jules (II) to his mother, Clementine (Larminat to GWP)
      -Mme L. B. Descorches to Jules de Beaumont, 29 juillet 1836 (she was the mother of Felicie de Bellou, who married Gustave de Beaumont's brother, Jules (II), postmarked Mortagne-sur-Huisne (Larminat to GWP)
      -la Couetterie [?], le 29 juillet 1836, Mme Descorches to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -mercredi, 10, A. de Bellou to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -Gervaise, 12 mai (6 pages), probably A. de Bellou to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 23 Xbre, L. B. Descorches, probably to Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -31 dec. 1846, Edouard de Beaumont, son of Gustave and Clementine, to his grandfather, Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 30 dec. 1847, Pont leroy, Edouard de Beaumont to his grandfather, Jules de Beaumont; this letter also contains one from Olivier to the same grandfather (Larminat to GWP)
      -le Guillet, 19 8bre 48, Edouard de Beaumont to his grandfather, Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, le 24 7bre, lundi, Edouard de Beaumont to his grandfather, Jules de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -Vienne, 28 8bre 1849, Edouard de Beaumont to his grandfather (Larminat to GWP)
      -le Guillet ce 31 janvier 1850, Edouard de Beaumont to his grandfather (Larminat to GWP)
    - c. Correspondence and Documents of Clementine de Lafayette, Comtesse de Beaumont, wife of Gustave de Beaumont (identified by Mme de Larminat) (Larminat to GWP) (Box 1)
      -negative photostat [?] of note in Mary Mottley's hand [?]: "Mon mari bien aime a recu le Saint Sacrement dans sa chambre a coucher a Cannes etendu sur sa chaise longue le six avril 1859. Le 16 du meme mois il a rendu le dernier soupir a sept heures et un quart du soir." (Larminat to GWP)
      -undated, Paul de Beaumont, son of Gustave and Clementine, to his mother (Larminat to GWP)
      -jeudi, 13 juin, Paul de Beaumont to his mother (Larminat to GWP)
      -undated, Paul de Beaumont to his mother (Larminat to GWP)
      -letter to her granddaughter, Marie (daughter of Antonin de Beaumont, son of Gustave and Clementine), letter with mourning band, dated Viantais, ce 9 mars 1885 (6 pages) (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 6 juin, letter to Marie, her granddaughter (8 pages) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Beaumont, ce 19 janvier 1886, letter to Marie (8 pages) (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 12 mai 1886, last letter to Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -see also elsewhere, especially letter from Mary Mottley (of 4 mars 1859 to Clementine de Lafayette); likewise the letter of H. Thion of 23 Decembre 1864, announcing Mary Mottley's death. (Larminat to GWP)
    - d. Edmond de Lafayette brother of Clementine de Lafayette, and so brother-in-law of Gustave de Beaumont (Box 1)
      -13 juin 1872, letter to his sister, Clementine de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -Belgique, ce 4 octobre 1886, letter to his nephew, the oldest son of Gustave, Antonin (Larminat to GWP)
      -undated letter to his niece (identified by Mme de Larminat as her mother, Marie de Beaumont, daughter of Antonin, so great-niece of Edmond de de Lafayette) (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 20 septbre 1886, rue de Rome 72, Paris, letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -20 nov. 1880 or 1886 [?], letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -1er mai 1887 [?], letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -undated letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -Chavaniac-Lafayette, ce 6 octobre 1887, note to his to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, 8 avril 1888, letter to Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -6 octobre 1888, note to hls great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -undated note to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 1er avril 1889, letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 14 Novembre 1889, rue de Rome 72, letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 14 decembre 1889, letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 23 Xbre [?], Paris, 1889, letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 22 avril 1890, letter to his great-niece, Marie (Larminat to GWP)
      -ce 1er Novembre 1890, rue de Rome 72 (Larminat to GWP)
      -faire-part of the death of Edmond de Lafayette (Larminat to GWP)
    - e. Family letters to Gustave de Beaumont (Box 1)
      -Achille de Beaumont to Gustave de Beaumont in England, dated Viantais, 22 juin, postmarked 23 juin 1837 (Larminat to GWP)
      -8 mai, postmarked [?] 1837, Jules de Beaumont to his son, Gustave, in England (Larminat to GWP)
      -Beaumont-la-Chartre, ce 27 mai, Jules de Beaumont to his son, Gustave, in England (Larminat to GWP)
      -Beaumont, ce 8 juin, Jules de Beaumont to Gustave in England (Larminat to GWP)
      -Beaumont-ce mercredi (no year), letter trom his wife, Clementine de Lafayette, on the votes obtained by Gustave and others in an election (1839?) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Viantais, ce 24 mai 1855, Francois to his uncle Gustave de Beaumont (Larminat to GWP)
      -see also elsewhere
    - f. Gustave de Beaumont to his family (Box 1)
      -undated letter presumably written by Gustave de Beaumont on the occasion of his mother's birthday; enclosed in this letter are now two songs presumably of Gustave's composition. The typed poem, I am told, is taken from the Beaumont genealogy, and the column of 13 refers to 13 children--GWP (Larminat to GWP)
      -Gustave de Beaumont to his wife, Clementine, listed under D.IV.r. (p. 102b) (Larminat to GWP)
  - Tocqueville - Beaumont correspondence, 1803-1830; 3 (Box 1)
    -5 oct. 1828, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont? (Note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -7 dec. 1828, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat)
    -10 mars 1829, "lundi", Versailles, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat)
    -18 mars 1829, "mercredi matin", Versailles?, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat)
    -30 aout 1829, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat)
    -15 sept. 1829, Versailles, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat) (also White extract from?)
    -19 sept. 1829, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat)
    -4 oct. 1829, Neuchatel, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat)
    -25 oct. 1829, Gray, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat)
    -26 nov. 1829, Versailles, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat) (see also C.I.a.2.)
    -8 mai 1830, Versailles, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat) (see also C.I.a.2.)
    -16 mai 1830, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (original, from Larminat) (see also C.I.a.2.)
  - Tocqueville & Beaumont correspondence with others, 1803-1830; 4 (Box 1)
    -4 April 1814, Paris, Tocqueville to Abbe Lesueur (White extract from?)
    -6 July 1817, Metz, Tocqueville to Lesueur (White extract from?)
    -28 July 1817, Tocqueville to Lesueur (White extract from?)
    -16 April 1820, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -20 avril 1820, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -18 juin 1820, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -3 juillet 1820, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -27 July 1820, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -21 juin 1821, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -2 aout 1821, Lesueur to Edouard de Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -3 9bre 1821, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -11 June 1822, Lesueur to Edouard de Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -5 July 1822, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -16 July 1822, Lesueur to Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -3 Aug. 1822, Lesueur to Edouard de Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -5 Aug. 1822, Lesueur to Edouard de Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -25 Aug. 1822, Lesueur Song (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -5 7bre 1822, Lesueur to Edouard de Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -13 7bre 1822, Lesueur to Edouard de Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -14 7bre 1822, Lesueur to Edouard de Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -16 7bre 1822, Lesueur to Edouard de Tocqueville (GWP extract from Redier MSS)
    -8 Sept. 1824, Lesueur to Tocqueville (note by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
    -24 Aug. 1826, Amiens, Tocqueville to Eugene Stoffels [?] (White extract from ?)
    -5 July 1827, Versailles, Tocqueville to Edouard de Tocqueville (White extract from ?)
    -27 mars 1828, Versailles, Tocqueville to Louis de Kergorlay (White extract from ?)
    -28 Oct. 1829, Gray, Tocqueville to Mother (White extract from ?)
  - Tocqueville & Beaumont and the July Revolution, 5 (Box 1)
    a. Beaumont manuscript untitled, about 40 pages on experiences in the July Revolution. (original, from Larminat)
    b. Beaumont, several pages of notes: 1er aout 1829, 9 Sept. 1830, 5 June 1832, 22 Xbre 1832. (original, from Larminat)
    c. "G. de Beaumont et la Revolution de Juillet" - 13 pages reflections, Sept? 1830. (original, from Larminat)
    d. see also E.IV.a. GWP notes on Tocqueville and Beaumont youth.
    e. see also A.VII. Tocqueville and Beaumont Correspondence. 1830-March 1831.
  - Tocqueville & Beaumont and their Prison Mission, 6 (Box 1)
    -for this see below, A.VII.B.1, and esp. B.I.e., B.I.f.
    -see also E.IV. a. GWP notes on Tocqueville and Beaumont youth.
  - Tocqueville - Beaumont correspondence, 1830- March 1831; 7 (Box 1)
    -"ce lundi matin" Le Menil, Tocqueville, to Mary Mottley (White extract from Redier MSS: Package 7, Dossier 4, Extract 7)
    -21 avril 1830, Versailles, Tocqueville to Charles Stoffels (GWP copy from Stoffels d'Hautefort typed copy)
    -26 "avril" [really August] 1830, Versailles, Tocqueville to Charles Stoffels
    -27 aout 1830, Metz, Eugene Stoffels to Tocqueville (fragment) (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:I.B.1.b.)
    -14 7bre 1830, Metz, Eugene Stoffels to Tocqueville (fragment) (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:I.B.1.b.)
    -24 7bre 1830, Metz, Eugene Stoffels to Tocqueville (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:I.B.1.b.)
    -25 7bre 1830, Runsing?, Henrion to Tocqueville (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:I.B.1.b.)
    -17 8bre 1830, Tocqueville to Henrion (copy of letter sent) (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:I.B.1.b.)
    -25 8bre 1830, Henrion to Tocqueville (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:I.B.1.b.)
    -29 8bre 1830, Metz, Eugene Stoffels to Tocqueville (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:I.B.1.b.)
    -4 9bre 1830, Paris, Tocqueville to Charles Stoffels (GWP - Mlle Stoffels d'Hautefort copy)
    -19 9bre 1830, Versailles, Tocqueville to Henrion (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, see GWP catalogue T:I.B.l.b)
    -30 decembre 1830, (Paris), Gustave de Beaumont to Mme Jules de Beaumont (GWP copy from Romanet)
    -2 mars 1831, (Metz?), Eugene Stoffels to Tocqueville (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:IV.E.1.)
    -(march?) 1831, Lesueur to Tocqueville (Bonnel from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; see GWP catalogue T:IV.E.1.)
  - Tocqueville - Beaumont Friendship, 8 (Box 2 (Oversize))
    -see GWP notes (in E.IV. a, b); also below B.I.a, b; C.I.a; C.VIII.
  - Tocqueville & Beaumont Portraits, etc., 9
    - a. The Young Tocqueville (see T. and B. in Am.)--cliche and 2 proofs. (Box 3)
    - b. Prefect and Secretary (see T. and B. in Am.)--2 cliches and 2 proofs. (Box 3)
    - c. Alexis de Tocqueville (Chasseriau) (see T. and B. in Am.)--2 negatives and 5 proofs. (Box 2 (Oversize))
    - d. Gustave de Beaumont at 35 (see T. and B. in Am.)--cliche and 2 proofs. (Box 3)
    - e. Gustave de Beaumont in 1848 as member of the National Assembly. (Box 2 (Oversize))
    - f. Gustave de Beaumont as Ambassador and Member of the Institut de France. (Box 2 (Oversize))
    - g. Gustave de Beaumont in the 1850's. (Box 2 (Oversize))
    - h. Beaumont-la-Chartre Chateau (Beaumont)--cliche and proof. (Box 3)
    - j. Beaumont-la-Chartre (Romanet)--cliche and proof. (Box 3)
    - k. Photo of unidentified Tocqueville portrait. (Box 1)
    - l. Photo of the Chateau de Tocqueville in 1930: small original positive, plus negative enlargement and 3 contact proofs. (Box 1)
    - m. Photo negative and positive of title page of De la Democratie en Amerique, 1835 (Box 1)
    - n. Negatives and prints of passages in Yale manuscript of De la Democratie en Amerique (Box 1)
    - o. Carte-de-visite portrait of Alexis de Tocqueville. (Box 1)
    - p. Photos said to be of portraits of Tocqueville and his wife. (Box 1)
    - q. Chateau de Tocqueville: postcards, etc. (Box 1)
    - r. Photo of Yale manuscript of Democratie, boxed. (Box 1)
    - s. The Chateau de Tocqueville in 1857, par Rivet. (Larminat to GWP) (Box 2 (Oversize))
    - t. Photos of 2 Beaumont sketches of Cannes in 1859. (Larminat to GWP) (Box 2 (Oversize))
    - u. Lithograph of Tocqueville by Leon Noel mounted (acquired by purchase) (Box 1)
    - v. Two small cartes-de-visite, both labelled Alexis de Tocqueville, but one perhaps of a brother? Also a small reproduction of Herve de Tocqueville. (Larminat to GWP) (Box 1)
- AMERICAN TRIP, APRIL 1831--APRIL 1832; B.
  - Letters and Reports, 1
    - B.I.a.1. Tocqueville Letters Home, 1831-1832 ("published") (Box 4)